this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software are you a tech savvy developer
with an inquisitive mind SC radio has an
opening for a new volunteer host to join
the team and produce five episodes per
year
contact show editor Robert bloomin at
Robert bloomin at gmail.com for details
hello my name is Adam Conrad for
software engineering radio today we have
Chris McCord talking about live view in
Phoenix Chris McCourt is an architect at
Dockyard the creator of elixirs web
framework Phoenix and author of
programming Phoenix 1.4 and
metaprogramming elixir for the pragmatic
bookshelf Chris holds a bachelor's
degree in computer science and has
extensive web development background you
can find him travelling the globe
speaking at conferences giving workshops
and advocating for elixirs budding
community Chris thanks for coming on
today so I want to get started by
talking about the whole ecosystem of
elixir in Phoenix you've contributed
primarily to the Phoenix framework which
we've talked about previously in episode
349 I'd also like to take a step back
and talk about elixir as well and go
through the whole stack so we did have a
previous discussion on elixir on episode
336 but if you could just give me a
brief overview of elixir in Phoenix
sure so language so it was started in
2011 I believe it when I say young but
it's actually quite stable at this point
you know it's been 100 and use in
production for at least five years now
by many companies but look sir itself
runs on the Erlang virtual machine so a
lot of times we can't talk about it
looks or without talking about Erling
and you think of like elixir kind of
like how closure runs on the JVM elixir
runs on the Erlang VM so much like we're
used to these JVM based languages we
kind of get to bootstrap the language
everything that's available so elixir
didn't have to reinvent the wheel and
kind of you know build a standard
library build web server but a bunch of
libraries it was able to come in and
take advantage of the Erlang VM so looks
are specifically and early and give us
kind of a unique paradigm for
development so it's not only a
functional language but it has a
concurrency model that has pre-emptive
scheduling so it allows us to scale to
you know millions of users per server
and really build distributed systems and
much different way compared to most
modern languages so be happy to get into
the details there but kind of the big
goal with elixir was building on the
Erlang heritage some modern features
with polymorphism with a modern build
tools a package manager and kind of like
all of the modern features of the
language we'd expect today but building
on kind of all this innovation the
Erlang as has proven out for the last
thirty years so that's the lick sir and
Phoenix is kind of like the de-facto web
framework for elixir
so I started Phoenix well before elixir
was one oh and I believe Phoenix went
100 in 2015 but it's been four years now
I have to go back and look but Phoenix
itself similar elixir at this point is
kind of you know a tried-and-true
has many success cases out there
powering companies like bleacher report
companies you know at a high scale with
you know hundreds of millions of
visitors so at this point we've kind of
you know proven to the world that were
it would be successful and give people
kind of unique advantages and I still
consider us kind of in this emergent
market share but we're hoping to you
know continue to advocate and grow where
we can and so you had actually worked in
the Rails space before is that correct
that's correct so if you heard at all
familiar with Phoenix and in rails from
ruby you will probably see a lot of
similarities there so the creator of
elixir Josey of Elam was on actually was
on the rails core team and
professionally I had worked building
primarily rails applications for six
years prior to starting Phoenix so I
think that you can see a lot of we
borrowed a lot of good ideas and I think
we also learned a lot from so we
borrowed borrowed a lot of the good
things from rails and we also you know
try to take the lessons that we learn
from
maybe the not-so-great experiences that
we had implied that to to the framework
okay and so then how did you know that
there was an opportunity for a web
framework were you were you looking at a
lick sir and saying okay this might be a
good opportunity for a language that
needs a web framework or were you
looking for to create a web framework
and then elixir happened to be the
language that that worked for that yes I
had no I don't like you know standing
where I am today it's very bizarre
because I had no plans to kind of be
where I'm at but so initially I was
trying to do a lot of real-time events
with Ruby and rails so you know I was
working at a consultancy and more and
more of our client requirements for
coming down to do kind of real-time
events in web applications I mean I love
Ruby at the time and you know so I was
trying to see how I can make the
real-time web work with Ruby and rails
it's kind of where all this started and
I quickly found out that that was not
going to be a viable path so I had
worked on a library to do kind of
real-time updates with rails and just
what I knew it wasn't going to scale and
it wasn't going to be reliable so at
that point in time you know I started
looking around to say like you know if I
want to build the kinds of real-time
applications that I know I need to build
you know what what's the best option and
especially what's the best option that
kind of gives me the the feeling of you
know this quote-unquote mystical you
know productivity and enjoyment of
coding that I hadn't known from Ruby so
it's kind of where it started so I was
looking around like I tried go initially
over like a winter break and that just
didn't feel right to me you know is more
of a feeling thing I I think go you know
you could write web applications that
scale and that a real-time with go but I
tried to go for a couple weeks I looked
at rust and ultimately I found an
article on Erlang in the context of
whatsapp you know they had just been
acquired for like 20 billion dollars and
I had seen that they had been running
like ten million or millions of users
per server I forget the number at this
point and that kind of piqued my
interest like how are they running you
know millions of connections on a single
server and I found out that they were
using this language called Erlang and
that's when I had remembered that Joe is
a villain from the rails core team had
retired from the rails core team to go
started
and that's where kind of just it piqued
my memory like you know when he went off
in 2011 to start his own language I
didn't really follow that development
just thinking like oh what's this what's
this crazy idea that he's doing but
Erlang reminding me that Jose Jose had
gone and created this language but it
licks her to run on the Erlang VM so
that's kind of when I got excited by the
prospect of scalability with Erlang and
I remembered elixir was this this little
thing that was started so I think it was
just kind of like the right timing there
to pick up a lick sir when it was very
young and I got hooked on elixir
immediately I fell in love with the
language so all I needed to do in order
to use it for everything I wanted to
build was write a web framework so it's
kind of how that happened it was more
like a hobby labor of love like I found
this language and to build real-time web
apps I needed to build a framework
because none existed in the lips ER at
the time so that was kind of the start
just kind of like humble hoppy projects
and people started using it and here we
are today and as part of that work in
trying to create real time applications
Live View is now a big part of that
experience so I want to shift gears over
to Live View since that's one of the
bigger features you're starting to
launch with with Phoenix so could you
just give us a quick overview of what
Live View is and what inspired you to
create it yes so live view is a way to
build kind of rich interactive
applications without having to write
JavaScript because one of my pain points
working at my previous consultancy was
just every single page app that we ended
up writing ended up being you know
taking ten times as long and being ten
times as hard to write for seemingly
little gain like a lot of times we just
had some kind of interactive features we
wanted to write the only way to
accomplish out it was to write a bunch
of JavaScript and adopt a JavaScript
framework so I was trying to that's what
I was trying to kind of accomplish with
my real-time rails features was how can
i how can I have real-time features
without writing JavaScript so the the
inspiration was there from the beginning
when I was looking around other
languages but live you only recently
happened so it's been in development for
about a year but you know it took us we
had to build all the plumbing with
phoenix web layer phoenix is real-time
layer phoenix pub/sub so we had all
these building blocks that allowed us
to kind of last year go back and
accomplish the original vision of the
kind of thing I was trying to solve with
Ruby which is being able to write
real-time applications server rendered
but giving you almost all of the
benefits that you would come to expect
from a single page app so that's really
what live yous about is being able to
write applications that are server
rendered but and give you much fewer
trade-offs and much more benefits and I
think that you would imagine I think
when people kind of originally hear this
idea they think it's crazy they think it
won't scale well they think it's gonna
perform poorly they think it's gonna be
a bad UX and I think we can actually
show that we can be single-page apps for
a lot of use cases compared to you know
something that you write by hand and
let's say react or amber
so what inspired live you to be created
and how is it involved from lightweight
systems like pjax or turbolinks
so for example with rails we had turbo
links as a lightweight solution for
interactivity on the client side is this
the equivalent for Phoenix and how has
it evolved since that model the
inspiration came from you know what I
was trying to accomplish in Ruby and
rails originally was you know how do I
render or how do i how do I perform
real-time updates without what having to
adopt a single page app and all that
complexity so it's rooted in what I was
trying to solve with Ruby you know seven
six seven years ago but we weren't able
to try to accomplish that until about a
year ago in Phoenix because we had to
build the web framework and the real
time layer and the pub/sub layer we had
to do all the building blocks first and
yeah that's what I'm able to us to to
get to the state where we could start
trying to accomplish this so the
motivation was how can we get the
real-time features that we have come to
expect from modern web applications
without the complexity of a single page
app because there's a lot of complexity
there to get kind of the UX that you're
that you're going for
so how it's different though from
turbolinks and pjax is I think it's it's
a comparison that we see folks make a
lot kind of looking on the outside and
so I think there are some overlap but
it's very minimal so the overlap is
turbolinks and pjax allow you to update
the page without a full refresh and
that's kind of the where the comparison
starts and stops so so in that light
they are the same
as far as not doing the full page
refresh but turbulence really is a
stateless approach and that's the big
difference with live you because live
you is stateful so with turbo links you
know you're doing an HTTP request and
you're with Ajax and then you're either
not rendering the layout or you have the
JavaScript just strip the layout and you
just do it like a body inner HTML
replace so it's kind of a very simple
model that gives you maybe a snappier
feel web page but it's still a stateless
request response where live view is
actually kind of like the react
programming model that we put on the
server so we're running a stateful
process we call elixir very light
threads processes but we're running a
stateful program per browser tab running
on the server for every user and that
allows us to do things that like
turbolinks model just can't do so one of
the best examples is if you're trying to
build let's say some event queue or some
some real-time system on the backend
that like as an event happens you want
to update the user's web page well with
turbolinks the only real way to
accomplish that would be to have like
the Ajax just pull the server over and
over and rerender but with live view we
have a running program running on the
server and as those events happen we
just update our templates and the UI's
could update for the user so I think
this bi-directional stateful difference
is the key that kind of unlocks the
potential for Live View so it's gotta
allow us to kind of do all these and the
optimizations that we can go into and
it's it's what allows us to be much
faster latency wise because we're
running this over a WebSocket connection
so we don't have all this HTTP overhead
we don't have to hit the databases often
so I think it's a very different
approach compared to pjax and turbolinks
even though on the surface there may be
some comparison if you're looking at
just kind of the not having to reload
the page kind of mindset so in
understanding the model here for live
view what I'm starting to understand is
that fundamentally something seems wrong
with JavaScript in JavaScript
development for client to server
interactions what do you think is wrong
with JavaScript yeah so I want to
carefully answer this because you know I
do think a JavaScript allows us to do a
lot of things that are impossible to do
otherwise so
I don't want to put down an entire
ecosystem and but I do think that a lot
of us have experienced this pain of
modern JavaScript development so I think
what I personally feel so I'm gonna come
in this form like this personal pain
perspective so I've worked at
consultancies for my entire professional
career and so I've had insights to you
know many dozens of different
applications application domains
business models and every time we've
gone all in on a single page app from
from my experience it has always been
way more complex then it's kind of
server rendered counterpart way bug
you're way harder to me you know
actually keep up with the pace of change
because of the JavaScript JavaScript
community by the time you ship your
product may have just changed the the
framework that is now kind of the de
facto way to go or even the framework
that you chose may have had breaking
changes so it's I think a combination of
things but this is all to say that folks
adopt single page applications I think
for good reasons like we have valid
business reasons to say we need to have
a rich experience here so one of the
obvious ones I'd like to give is like a
registration form right like we want to
have client-side validations because
we're trying to increase conversions to
users signing up or buying a product
like we have good reasons for taking on
this pain but for me I feel like a lot
of us take on this complexity in pain
because we have to accommodate these few
features right like we need this
interactivity here we need this common
sighted validation here we need to have
a chat box here but the rest of our app
could just be server rendered or
otherwise so I think a lot of us buy
into the complexity for good reasons but
it's a huge burden where if we had an
alternative that existed that gave us
you know these these rich bits of user
rich UX that we could otherwise you know
operate with a normal server render
model that's kind of the dream that we
sell with live view and in practice
we're seeing that that pan out so I
think the pain comes from just overly
complex solutions trying to write
stateful applications on the client and
then put you into the distributed state
problems so I think that's just the
model itself single page apps is just
inherently
complex and that's kind of what leads to
the pain and based on what you're saying
it sounds like it's an additive solution
not a replacement so in other words you
can use JavaScript in some places and
live you and others or even on the same
page yeah you can so we give you the an
escape hatch to write JavaScript as
needed so you know the goal for us is to
do as much for you as we can but there
is a happy medium like if you're trying
to do charting you can use a you know a
charting library and feed it data from
the live view and still render the rest
of the page with you know server render
HTML so those two worlds do coexist and
then understanding a bit more how Live
View works is live view JavaScript or
elixir or a combination of both so it's
a combination of both so I think at the
moment it's like 1,300 lines of
JavaScript that we write for you that
powers all of this so it's actually not
a lot of JavaScript and one of our
explicit goals is to you know not create
a JavaScript framework in our effort to
not have folks use a JavaScript
framework right so if it's a 300
megabyte I'm sorry 300 kilobyte payload
to load live view then you know we will
have lost right that doesn't make sense
so our goal is to so really the real
innovation happens on the server with
live view but ultimately it does require
JavaScript on the client to to update
the page but I just want to make it
clear though that what we do sin on the
initial page render is just HTML so if
even if your if your web crawler or you
have JavaScript disabled you will get a
rendered HTML page so there isn't any of
this like skeleton page that we hydrate
later it's just an HTML render so
there's a lot of benefit that we get
even if we have JavaScript running
behind the scenes once we connect to the
server right so even immediately one of
the benefits with Live View is for SEO
purposes since you have a full HTML page
you can now immediately distribute that
where as opposed to a s.p.a you might
have some challenges with being able to
fully showcase all the content that's
available yeah exactly and I think the
other thing I'm gonna highlight with
kind of going along lines of what's
wrong with JavaScript I want to also
highlight just in general I mentioned
the complexity in in the model of just a
single page app like you just it's
inherently more complex because now you
have client-server interaction
you have to define all those contracts
what those payloads look like how to
render that on the client and what live
you allows us to do is not only skip all
the single page app JavaScript
complexity but it also removes an entire
abstraction layer of just web
development which i think is actually
really important I didn't actually fully
appreciate this until after LiveView was
written and we I went back and tried to
use it as a user to appreciate like just
how much actually falls away so if you
imagine even from a simple the simplest
feature that you could write for a
client site app you could have some
level of server communication right so
you have to create some kind of HTTP
endpoint whether it's a JSON API whether
it's graph QL you have to immediately
start writing this kind of glue code
between the client and server so it's
gonna involve setting up the route and
your router it's going to involve you
know figuring out the naming for the
controller so now you're doing you're
making naming decisions and these are
all easy to do but you're making all
kinds of decisions just to get kind of
these client-server worlds glued
together and then you're having to write
kind of what the payload looks like on
the server how do you serialize the data
structures in your an elixir or whatever
language you're using and then you can
send back to the client the client has
to also be aware of this kind of payload
contract so there's all these like
decisions and touch points just to get a
message to the server and back to the
client or with live you that actually
completely falls away so I mention it's
kind of like react on the server so
there is no there are no you know routes
once you're connected you're just
interacting you annotate your DOM and
those send events they get called on
your elixir code and all of that happens
for you so this entire router controller
payload contract layer just completely
disappears and that vastly simplifies
the programming model of building a web
app it's kind of it feels like cheating
is what I like to say and it's kind of a
even for me as the creator it feels like
it shouldn't be possible once you kind
of get in this mode of writing
applications this way and you had
mentioned that it really didn't surface
for you until you actually started
writing an application what was the
first application you used to test this
out yeah so the very first one was a
this quote/unquote client-side
validation use case just because that's
what so often I've been hit with per
when building out apps so it's just like
you know you you have surfer Ranger HTML
and you you everything works as it
should everybody's happy except for this
registration process that you want you
as a users typing you want to tell them
that they can't you know put a hyphen in
their user name or that their emails
already taken and that's where you're
like you immediately now spin all these
cycles on like setting up web pack do
you bring your act endued you know pick
a framework and assuming you can do that
like how do you get like localization
down to the client so you anyway you
start adopting really a mountain of
complexity just to get like one of your
pages kind of somewhat you know
interactive so that was a very first
approach for me was like a non optimized
live view where I took my elixir code
that I'm used to writing for a server
rendered no JavaScript registration page
and I said you know what if I could just
take that same HTML I'm used to writing
that shows you your validation errors
but you have to click Save first but if
I could just rerender that on the server
let's say on every key press and that
was kind of the model I took initially
in kind of prototype doubt this idea and
so yeah that's where it all started and
now you know that was a it was a very
naive approach we were rendering all the
HTML we're sending the HTML over the
wire on every keystroke
it was very expensive but since then
we've been able to introduce
optimizations that actually makes it in
a lot of the cases better than the best
handwritten jason that you could try to
spin up in a single page app even though
it seems like that would be impossible
and so for our listeners are there any
sort of sample applications or ideas
that they could use if they wanted to
try out just a starter version of life
you just to get going with something
there's a phoenix frenzy calm frenzy
with a ph Dockyard just hosted this
competition for the community I think we
had like 30 some close to 40 entries of
people just building whatever they
wanted and competing for the best
application so that's kind of like a
showcase of examples people will build a
lot of games which is kind of you know
surprising like you know gaming was not
an original target for us but like you
know people have built chess they've
built Tetris they've built like actually
compelling games out of the server
rendered approach so that's a good place
to check out and
the underneath my github there's a
Phoenix live you example repo that has
maybe half a dozen applications where
you know we show the real-time
validation there's a thermostat with
like the current weather we show
pagination infinite scrolling it's kind
of just like some basic things that you
would you would try to do an app right
like we support push date as well so
there's an example in there of
pagination with push date so you're able
to do next page next page with action
without actually having to experience a
full page reload so kind of that's kind
of where maybe the turbolinks idea comes
from but I think we have a good example
between phoenix frenzy and then the live
view example repo that at least get
people started in general it sounds like
writing a component in live view it
feels like writing a component in react
or view so would you say that if you're
considering using react review or some
other major SP a framework that live
view could be an interesting substitute
yes absolutely so yeah live view
supports a the same kind of component
idea so you can write reusable
components and i think any any
interactive application that that you
may consider it for let's say reactor
view i think live view is at least worth
a look you know we like to say that
there there is a limit at which i think
it makes sense to write a single page
app so i think our goal isn't to say
that we obviate all single page
applications and frameworks but i do
think that we remove a large class of
them from requiring a single page app
framework so i think you know if you're
trying to build google docs absolutely
you need to write client code you know
if you're so if you're building kind of
ambitious just stop like experiences by
all means you know pick up one of these
great frameworks but i think there's a
large class of applications that
probably the majority of us are building
that kind of fit in the middle where you
need some you know bits of interactivity
and i don't know where the limit is yet
so it's kind of a case-by-case basis but
the limit keeps going further out so i
think a year ago i said you know i
didn't know if you could build a chat
application with live view and have that
be like an effective experience but at
this point you want people are building
chat apps and they're doing it
effectively with
low server utilization the data payloads
on the wire for the chat up probably
often be a equivalent react chat out
that you will try to build so it's hard
to say where the the line exists but I
do think there it's at least worth a
look if you're building kind of any kind
of interactive application maybe to help
the listeners figure out the differences
if we could dive into the render cycle
maybe see how the differences are
between Live View and a traditional SP a
sure yes so I think the render cycle is
what is our like secret sauce and I can
credit a Joe saving the creative elixir
has worked on really almost all of the
optimizations that make 5u amazing so
I'm a huge credit but what we're able to
do is we're able to take the you know
you write a live view template like
you're used to writing any other server
rendered HTML template and the way that
we make that performant for all these
updates because if you imagine you as a
users typing a character or clicking a
button you know every change they make
we have to rerun it out on the server
and that's the program model just like
react right yeah any change you make to
your state react renders your template
and it does a V Dom virtual Dom diff to
make it efficient but on the server the
way we make this fast and efficient is
we we have the same approach where you
use change your state we render your
template but our templates internally do
change tracking so we'll actually only
execute the elixir code that has changed
so it seems like it's expensive on the
server but we actually only at runtime
execute the code that's necessary to be
executed and then the data on the wire
we almost do like a virtual Dom on the
server so the data on the wire that we
send isn't your whole template even
though the programming model seemingly
is we render the whole template we
actually only send a diff of the content
of the template that changed on any
given change and all that content is
only it doesn't contain any of that the
static HTML so I mentioned it's kind of
like virtual Dom except it's way more
efficient than virtual Dom on the server
because we don't we're not Dom aware so
if you have a bunch of HTML on your
template and then you have like a
dynamic class on it the only thing that
we would send down as the diff is this
string that changed for that class name
not you know all the div and table rows
and then what we do on the client it's
similar to react this you know react has
a virtual down on the client which
allows it to do an efficient Dom patch
we use a library called morph Dom which
allows us to it's very similar to
virtual Dom except it uses just pure Dom
interfaces but we take on the client we
patched the Dom by taking the diff from
the server we recompute what the
template should look like on the client
and then we take the current Dom on the
client and we say here's what the Dom
shouldn't look like now and then morph
thumb figures out how to apply that in
the most efficient way possible so so
one example is if you just changed the
inner text of like an h1 tag and you
gave it a hole template it would compare
the hole Dom structures and ultimately
just execute like h1 inner HT they were
sorry inner text equals new value so the
more stoma allows us to do an efficient
Dom patch just like react so at least
hopefully I get some insight into in the
model this actually sounds similar to
dirty checking with something like
angular because you're actually seeing
comparing both sides to say well what is
the difference it's changed and so is
the server then serving as the dirty
check reference if that makes sense yes
exactly so it's been many years since
its I was I was involved in angular and
angular one days but yes that actually
sounds like a good analogy and this is
kind of I touched on earlier with you
know how turbo links is the stateless
for staple model this is why it's very
different because we have this state on
the server we actually know what changed
right it's not like the client you could
you could mirror it or you could try to
recreate a live you like approach and we
see other communities doing this over
stateless HTTP but that would involve
the client sending up its stay on every
interaction so the client could pass
let's say all this the quote unquote
State on every interaction and you would
have that and your callbacks on the
elixir side but that would not give you
the stateful dirty tracking or the
optimizations that were able to do so
since we actually we know what change
because we have this process up and
running for the entire lifecycle so
that's kind of what enables all this
and what's interesting now that you're
saying this and you've mentioned this
multiple times that this is a stateful
model whereas the other forms are
stateless the interesting thing here is
that elixir is certainly touted as a
functional language and anytime you talk
about state to a functional programmer
they're going to wonder you know is this
the right way of doing things so how do
you handle State in a way that still
maintains a functional paradigm yeah so
fortunately for us elixir in our line
we're built on these primitives so we
handle it exactly the way it's supposed
to be handled okay and if that sounds
weird but there is only one way to build
stateful applications in elixir knurling
so it's not it's not a unusual approach
like that the way we do it is with
primitives built into Erlang standard
library so this is all to say that it's
still you know a mutable state and it's
still a functional paradigm but the all
these primitives were figured out thirty
years ago
hurling was built in the 80s so they
took this kind of a mutable functional
language with this unique concurrency
model and over the course of X amount of
years they they figure out they were
writing stateful applications in the
same way so they wrap that up into a
library that we now if refer to as OTP
and Phoenix and elixir and with live
view we take advantage of all that so
the way that we're actually doing this
something elixir side is very natural
and not unusual at all it is the way you
write a stateful application and elixir
it just happens to be you know connected
to a browser tab on the other side but
it's very natural and has been you know
shown to be robust and scale out to
millions of users and so does that also
mean that you don't need redux if you're
worrying about state management and the
elixir server can handle the state
management it almost sounds like not
only do you not need react or view you
can also swap out redux as well since
the server is now the central store for
state yes exactly and I think that's
what's interesting to me too about
elixir is I think a lot of the a lot of
the problems that are being solved in
the client-side with Java scripts and a
lot of the pain weeks
with library churn is because these
primitives that we have let's say on the
elixir side and in other languages don't
exist in JavaScript so you see the
communities kind of come up with
libraries like redux which allows you to
my understanding at least I'm not a user
of it allows you to like serialize
events and data flow through the system
if I'm not mistaken these primitives
just exists in elixir right so the way
that we build stateful applications in
the lick sir naturally lends itself to
like prior are unicef concurrency
receive messages in serial so I think a
lot of these these solutions that we see
in other languages just exist as part of
the platform which kind of a remove is
all these layers of trying to choose a
library and learn library it just
naturally kind of falls into the
programming model that we're used to
riding on the elixir side so is there an
ideal application that live view is
suited for so what I like to say is it's
especially well-suited I think for kind
of the boring business problems that
we're all solving over and over which is
a large class of applications so that's
not a very specific answer
I'd say it's from two sides if you're
writing a static HTML template
application today let's say that your
requirements are just render some
tabular data let's say now you have the
option just to make that real time
out-of-the-box with the same amount of
work so I think it unlocks potential for
applications that you're already used to
writing and it also allows you to
accomplish those more complex user
experiences in much less time so you
know any example of trying to do any
kind of real-time updates on the page
dashboards are a great example any time
you're trying to display information
that's frequently changing and you want
the client to update now you can just
write you know a single line in your
live view that subscribes to some
pub/sub events and then two long two
more lines of code and now your
dashboards just updating with you know
the current request for a second the
current weather you know current tickets
whatever you need for your business so I
think dashboards are a great example any
bits of rich interactivity like sign up
forms a check out is a great example
like building a commerce solution and
anytime I do anytime I check in to my
flight I always think this would be a
great life you experience because you
know you always expect the server has to
be there when you select your seats so I
think a large class of standard business
applications would work the only thing
that it's not good for would be
something that requires like offline
mode because clearly since we're server
powered if you can't connect to the
server and then that leaves you in kind
of a read-only state but I think that we
haven't found out where it's not a good
fit yet provided that you don't need
offline support or kind of like desktop
like functionality so there's no
opportunity to keep retrying or have it
talk to a local storage mechanism in the
interim or is that something for a
future iteration yes so we so to be
clear we keep retrying so it's actually
funny because I found out just like a
week ago that Google Docs doesn't work
offline I just assumed it did like I use
Google Docs as an example when I talk
about live view as like I still don't
think you would write Google Docs in
Live View to be clear but I always use
that as an example of here's clearly a
bad fit but I actually turned my Wi-Fi
off in my Google Doc which I assume
would be interactive when in a read-only
mode until I reconnected so this is all
to say that it's like a very gray area
but well but what live you will do is it
will it will make it will turn the page
into like will do like a CSS cursor
where you know that it would change the
pointer to an accessible cursor and it
will set a Phoenix disconnected class on
the live view container so by default
out of the box you get connection
recovery and you get the page the page
updates with a cut loading spinner and
with a CSS class that you can override
so so to be clear your app gracefully
quote-unquote degrades when it
disconnects but it becomes in like
read-only mode right you can't interact
with it so I do think there are some
possibilities to make that there are
possibilities for us to do some local
storage ideas but ultimately if we're
very limited because if there's any
logic around the user interaction that
logic lives in elixir
and we can't apply that yet to the
client so I'd say if you do need any
rich interaction offline and then it's
an obvious case to use a client side up
and I think that's it's not a problem
it's what the client side solutions are
good for it's like if you have to run
code on the client and then you've got
great options available and that makes
sense too because really in this time in
this year we're more worried about low
or bad connections rather than
absolutely no connection at all and so
you're saying that by having the ability
to do these optimistic retries if you do
have a bad connection or low service it
still allows it to have somewhat of a
seamless operation yeah and we have so
optimistic UI is another one where if
you want true optimistic UI we won't be
a good fit but we do have some
optimistic UI features and we do hope to
grow them as well so for example you can
when you submit a form you can annotate
the Dom to say swap out the form text
with you know new text like saving or
whatever you want to say so we do have
some optimistic UI features already in
place and I do think we can kind of push
the balance there but if you're trying
to physically render let's quote-unquote
render a template on the client when
you're offline in an optimistic way
that's just not going to work but along
this point I think a lot of folks
initially hear this offline mode and
then think oh well you know live use out
then but in my experience most the vast
majority of single page apps also don't
work offline and perform poorly when
there's bad latency so it's actually big
complexity buy-in even if you're all in
on a single page app - to fully go and
support offline mode so I think most
single page apps degrade very poorly
because they often expect the server to
be snappy so that a lot of times they
won't even do optimistic UI and you just
click Save and nothing happens and it's
it's a worse experience than just like
waiting for the regular form post
because you don't even get any browser
indication and there's also this this
issue of once you support offline mode
you have to handle data synchronization
on the client and server so anyway this
I think a lot of folks like to troll me
especially with like what about offline
so they either troll me or they they
legitimately think well since it doesn't
do offline mode it's not gonna be a good
fit for me but like I said by and large
that's a that's a complexity that you
have to adopt on a case-by-case basis
because it's not free to support offline
mode even if you have a single page app
right and even then being exhaustive
about what the feature sets are doesn't
negate the fact that in the real world
how often are people really creating
pure offline applications that have to
talk to a client-server model like I
said earlier it's it could be more about
low connection or bad connection rather
than no connection at all but you know
in my mind I also think one of the
upsides here is that you're showcasing
that live view isn't perfect for
everything in one of those cases is
offline are there other examples or
downsides to getting started with Live
View yes so you know offline is the
obvious is the obvious one I think you
know I mentioned that people are making
games which blows me away and I think is
awesome and it actually it's a really
fun way to I think do web programming so
in general I think gaming with live you
will be a cool way to teach elixir to
people because you know it's it's it's
way more enjoyable to you know see a
game running in a stateful you know you
work you can write a staple system and
then you can kind of show that off with
live view versus you know showing it to
a text console so that it does excite me
but I do think you know obviously if
you're trying to render something on the
client at the speed of keypress
interaction then that's gonna be a bad
fit for Live View because ultimately
there is going to be latency there right
we can't change the laws of physics yet
so anything that requires like I say cut
controlled inputs so if you're trying to
do validation at the speed of user
typing so you know as you if you're
trying to format a phone number or a
birthday at key press event
typing that requires java script and
that controlled input cases actually
works with Live View with our our
phoenix hook primitive you could write
five lines of JavaScript to do that
formatting as a user's typing but that's
not something that you would want to
send to the server because of the delay
just would be a bad experience so one of
the examples I had that was a clear
example of trying to push the bounds for
something that ultimately didn't work
was a typing tutor application so I
wrote a typing tutor that
you know a brown fox jumped over the log
or if you know whatever some basic
sentences and it just didn't work well
like that the application worked live
you pick up the events and showed red
errors where you typed but it became
clear that if a user expects as your
latency you know interaction at the
speed of key press at the at the browser
render of nth loop then this is going to
be a bad fit for live use so I think you
know what typing tutor is one example
that clearly was a bad fit so I think
anything that demands your zero latency
whether it's games or whether it's
different interaction with the keyboard
is gonna ultimately require people to
write JavaScript whether or not that
rules out let's say all gaming I don't
think so because a lot of like
turn-based games would be perfect for
live view and people in Phoenix friends
even wrote like someone did a flight
simulator where they actually rendered
SVG 3d environment deployed it and I was
able to use it across the internet and
it actually worked quite well so so
there's a gray area there but I'd say
anything that demands zero latency has
to be a client side up or it's just
gonna be a bad experience so I think
that's the biggest pitfall is just
trying to do things that don't account
for latency and we are trying to it's on
the roadmap it's not in place yet but
we're trying we want to add a latency
simulator in live view for development
exactly to address this purpose because
our goal for live view isn't for people
to write you know mediocre experiences
we want live view to be like full stop a
compelling solution that cannot that can
beat a single page app in some cases and
a big part of that is making sure people
build you know good web citizen
applications that you know don't expect
the user to be you know on localhost
so that is something that we want to
build in the live view to ensure that we
don't that we allow people to not hit
these pitfalls and so the mechanism you
use for this live connection is
WebSockets correct yep it's a single
WebSocket connection and we multiplex
different channels over that so so
ultimately like you could be running
multiple stateful live views and
components on a page but we only would
have one physical WebSocket connection
so because of that with these open
sockets is there any security concerns
with live view none that
are different than what you're used to
experiencing so internally we we
generate a token so there is this
two-step process where we render pure
HTML and then the client reconnects over
WebSockets back to the server and we
render the template and the way we
passed that setup is with a signed token
so you know standard rules apply here
where it's the same token be a based
authentication that you you would be
used to writing for JavaScript
applications so you know you want to be
using SSL and if you were to expose your
secret token that you sign all your keys
with obviously all your tokens would be
exposed but this is all to say this is
exactly the same same implications that
would apply to existing token based
security that you're you're likely using
for your reactor view applications right
and you had mentioned earlier too that
you're not hydrating the same HTML over
again you're you're actually producing
HTML like a full page even from the
beginning so does that mean there are
absolutely no concerns for SEO or are
there still issues with SEO that may not
be able to be fully addressed with live
view so there are no concerns
you could yourself make a make it behave
like a single page app where if you're
not connected yet you could render like
a loading dot dot dot page and then when
you connect you could have live you
render the regular page so otherwise by
default if you just write it like you
were note used to writing a template you
would just get a C SEO for free
. even if you it cur if you hit the
input with curl you're a good HTML yeah
so the only way that you would have
issues is if you intentionally wanted to
render the HTML content after the user
connects several web sockets so by
default if the the normal mode of
operation the normal way you would write
a template it was just work if you hit
the applications and with curl you would
get HTML but if you wanted to let's say
for micro optimization reasons render
like a loading screen first let's say
behind like a logged in interface where
you don't need to have an initial HTML
render you could do that but it's not
something that I have actually ever done
in practice but if you wanted to avoid
SEO wasn't a concern and you wanted to
more optimize your application you could
do so but the app by default is just
going to work and browsers are going to
get the HTML page that you render that
makes sense and so so now that we have a
full picture of the benefits the
downsides and sort of how this works
altogether someone's building an
application now they're using this for
their business logic for a dashboard how
do they go about testing Live View
components so we have a Phoenix live
view test library that ships with Live
View and it's pretty great because it
allows you to test drive your live views
without running a headless web browser
which in my experience is never a good
experience I mean I understand that it's
a necessity if you want to test you know
a JavaScript based application and you
want to you want to fully kind of smoke
test the app you need to kind of drive
it from a browser so I get it but that's
not something we want to push by default
because they're slow they're brittle
tests and my experience so what live you
test does is we've run a live view
elixir clients that acts just like the
JavaScript client that we have and it
consumes those dips from a WebSocket
connection just like your JavaScript app
does and you can test drive it in just
pure elixir code so you can like spin up
one of these things it's a staple
process you can send messages to it you
can broadcast events like a new chat at
like if you're right if you're at a chat
app you could broadcast a new message
and then you could assert that the the
chat live you now has that message
rendered on the page so you can test
drive it in a very fast way that doesn't
have all these like headless webkit cap
yachts right and because it's actually
sending the entire load that means that
in a way you could use this as a full
end-to-end solution you could actually
check out the entire HTML code and say
does this match the expectation I have
for what I'm seeing on the client-side
yeah exactly
and we don't ship with a HTML parser at
the moment so so we you just get a
string of HTML but what I do myself and
what a lot of people do is they just
bring in a HTML parser dependency and
that gives them like CSS selector based
tests within their live view tests
so it's not like you don't have to
assert against you an entire HTML
document you can actually do like
selector based tests like you know
within this IDE I expect this commented
to exist okay so that in that sense this
is definitely acting like a integration
testing framework or does this include
elements of unit testing integration
testing and end-to-end testing it
includes elements of them in general I'm
a fan of integration tests for your web
facing code so we do have a live
isolated it's literally called live
isolated test helper which allows you to
unit test a live view so basically like
Tessa lie to you that is isn't
necessarily like it won't go through the
whole router stack but for me just like
I recommend for regular controller tests
I recommend integration tests just
because that's the flow that the user is
going to take so the fact that I can
test HTML that a controller or a live
view renders to me isn't all that useful
because I might as well just go through
the whole stack because that's the same
step the users gonna take and it's the
same assertions so it's actually a
stronger test for me to do integration
tests and because it's because it's a
lexer as fast so it's it's gonna be just
gonna be fast so you might as well do it
and one of the things that that actually
reminds me of is in wrapping this up if
you want to provide a business case for
why live you might be a better choice
than say react or even just plain old
JavaScript can you give some insights
for example in doing a dashboard
application profiling between the before
and the after do you have a sense of
what kind of performance gains we've
seen with Live View so I don't have hard
numbers yet I will say probably like an
order of magnitude if I had to guess I
really believe if I can order magnitude
mine's a code reduction just based
strictly on lines of code and like I
said that doesn't account for also the
server-side code that you may not have
to write or that you could then get rid
of so I think speed of development
productivity is going to be unbeatable
compared to a single page app and also
data on the wire in actual latency we
can beat single page apps with because
of what I like to highlight is if you
imagine a you know world
last single-page application unless they
roll their own websocket api which most
don't
every Jayson interaction has to
authenticate the request it has to go
through the fetch the current user or
maybe do token authentication for just
every interaction right every post every
you know user is typing message and
that's expensive that's overhead that
you have to do for all requests for a
user but for Live View we authenticate
once and now every interaction that user
takes is over an existing web like
WebSocket connection so no HTTP overhead
no part in the session no authentication
we want to fetch the current user from
the database because we already have
them so I actually think from a
development speed standpoint and a user
experience standpoint it's
counterintuitive but I think we can
actually have a faster less latent user
experience with a server rendered app
compared to a single page app which i
think is very counterintuitive and we
also produce less data on the wire so
imagine if you wrote the most naive HTML
application that you could write and
then that data payload was smaller than
the best handwritten jason you could
write by hand and that's what you get
for free with live view so instead of
coming up with serialization formats
just the natural data optimizations that
fall out of the program model is like a
keyless payload that's gonna beat the
best handwritten jason you could write
so i think that there are clear business
wins here from whether it's a
development speed point of view or even
a user experience point of view and so
to wrap up if someone's now convinced
they want to use live view and they want
to get started you've got your
programming Phoenix book that's out
you've also got the keynote that you did
on live view on elixir comp 2019
are there any other resources you would
recommend to our listeners for getting
started with Live View so those are
great places to start the phoenix book
just very lightly touches on live view
because live view is still early it's
pre 1o so we weren't quite ready for the
phoenix book but we do talk about it in
the last chapter and we show examples
and we talk about the programming model
but it won't and won't go like end to
end as like a here's the full way to use
the live view live view itself if you
check out the heck stocks we actually
have a really really fantastic
documentation in live view like the
modular docs are huge and they show you
primitives and they talk about you
some best practices on using components
like we have we have stateful components
and we have stateless components and we
talked about both and when you would use
one or the other so I think you the
documentation actually is probably much
more robust than people think but that's
where I would start and then eventually
we want to go with like full-blown and
glut guides like the Phoenix guides but
it's definitely still early in the
process so I encourage folks to get
involved and definitely let us know
where we need to fill the gaps in great
thank you so much Chris today for coming
on to talk with us on software
engineering radio we will link in the
show notes to Chris's Twitter as well as
all these other links to the other
episodes including his keynote talks for
elixir conf and all the documentation
for Phoenix framework and live view
Chris thanks again thank you thanks for
listening to se radio an educational
program brought to you by Triple E
software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at Etsy - Radio net to
provide feedback you can comment on each
episode on the website or reach us on
LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through our
slack channel at SC radio.com
you can also email us at team @ SC -
radio net this and all other episodes of
se radio is licensed under Creative
Commons license 2.5 thanks for listening